Finding Aid for the Cole Family Papers LSC.0217
UCLA Library Special Collections
Cole Family papers
1833-1943
UCLA Library Special Collections
Cole family
LSC.0217
38.0 Linear Feet (76 boxes and 4 oversize boxes)
Cornelius Cole (1822-1924) practiced law in San Francisco (1850) before relocating to Sacramento in 1851 where he served as the district attorney of Sacramento City and County (1859-62). He was later elected as a Union Republican to the thirty-eighth Congress (1863-65), and as a Republican to the U.S. Senate (1867-73) where he served as the chairman for the Committee on Appropriations (Forty-second Congress). The collection consists of correspondence, business papers, clippings, photographs, scrap books, diaries, various writings by Cornelius and Olive Cole, and family memorabilia concerning the public and private career of Cornelius Cole and his family. The papers cover more than a century of American history including California politics, government and history, life in the Southwest, Civil War campaigns, railroads, and the crystallization of the new Republican party in Northern California.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lucretia (Cole) Waring, 1952.
Gift of Mrs. Franz Osthaus, 1956.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942326943606533
Biography
Cornelius Cole was born in Lodi, Seneca County, New York, September 17, 1822; graduated Wesleyan University, 1847; studied law and was admitted to the bar in Auburn, New York, 1848; moved to California, 1849; after working a year in the gold mines, began the practice of law in San Francisco, 1850; moved to Sacramento, 1851; served as district attorney of Sacramento City and County, 1859-62; moved to Santa Cruz in 1862; commissioned as a captain in the Union Army during the Civil War, 1863; elected Union Republican to the thirty-eighth Congress (1863-65); elected as a Republican to the U.S. Senate (1867-73); chairman, Committee on Appropriations (Forty-second Congress); resumed his law practice; moved to Colegrove, Los Angeles County, California, and retired from active practice, 1880; member Pioneer Society of California; died in Hollywood, California, November 3, 1924.
Biographical Narrative
It is not unusual for the papers of a man in public life to stand as a substantial piece of the history of his nation. But it is a rare thing for a collection of such papers to sweep across more than a century of that history and to illustrate and elucidate the varied events and personalities which come to life in the papers of Cornelius Cole and his family. They begin with the noise and emotions of political battles in New York State in the 1840s, and the clashing ambitions at the diggings in California. For Cole, the papers close with the anxiety and despair of the years just after the first World War; but the family papers continue the story into the midst of the world struggle that arose out of those years. During the greater part of this span of time, Cole was busily participating in, and for a decade, helping to mold the history of the United States.
A sense of immediacy permeates the papers. In the 1850s he sails via Panama to the lure of the California mines, edits a newspaper in Sacramento, consults with Collis P. Huntington and Leland Stanford there, and assists in the crystallization of the new Republican party in northern California. Elected to Congress in 1862, he exchanges the friendships of his home and family in Santa Cruz for the fevered excitement of Washington, D.C. in the midst of Civil War. There he talks with Grant and Lincoln, and hears the President speak at Gettysburg. His energy and ability secure his election as Senator from California in 1867. He witnesses the expulsion of Andrew Johnson and his followers, and the subsequent triumph of Grant and Radical Reconstruction. The Senator is a frequent visitor to the White House, not only for the brilliant receptions, but in the morning hours when the business of the administration is decided upon. He is a member of the inner circle not only because of his friendship with the President and his advisors. Cole is the Senator from California, now for the first time, a state of primary political importance in the councils of the nation. There is more to its name than the clink of gold. For the nation and therefore for the party and men who run the nation, it means mounting population, shipping, agriculture, and the network of railroads that pervades the political as well as the physical structure of the state. It is a time when Californians are seriously considered for places in the Cabinets of several Presidents; Cole's name is mentioned several times in this connection. When political pressures from the forces which control the state prevent the renomination of Cole, he does not withdraw from the public scene. His legal ability and useful political contacts make him a good choice for the litigants involved in the settlement of the Alabama claims. And while he stays on in Washington, D.C. in the late 1870s, he continues his friendships with men whose names bear the history of those years.
Even when he returns to his new home near Los Angeles in the 1880s, his experienced and critical mind keeps his name prominent in his community and his state. In California old friends call on him: the Grants, General Sherman and his wife, and the John A. Logans. Traveling to Washington, D.C., he meets President Arthur. In the 1890s, he again returns to the Capital which is now so different from what it was when he first saw it, and he meets President Cleveland there. Outside the halls of Congress, Cole assists in the legislation for the Los Angeles Harbor project, noting well the pressures applied by the supporters of the Santa Monica and San Pedro sites.
When many of his old friends and relatives pass from the scene during these years, Cole momentarily despairs and turns to his memories. His recollections of a busy life are given to the public in a volume of memoirs published in 1908. But the busy life is far from over. The anxiety and uncertainty of the first World War stimulate his old interests and energies, until his busy pen takes the place of his presence in public forums. The writing of these years is neither erratic nor meaningless. Men whose voices are respected by a great part of the nation write serious thoughts to Cole and welcome his opinions. The self-assurance and sometimes bitter partisanship through which he observed and then dismissed Andrew Johnson, William McKinley, and Theodore Roosevelt, is now turned against Woodrow Wilson. Like many of his countrymen, he finds in the calm presence of Warren G. Harding a source of hope and domestic stability which the past years had so disturbed. In these last years, he continues to gather the honor of his neighbors, as a California Pioneer, and of his fellow countrymen, as the last survivor of the government of Abraham Lincoln. In 1922, he receives an ovation in the House of Representatives. Having cast his first vote for James K. Polk, he casts his last one for Calvin Coolidge.
Magnificent as it is, the story of the Cole papers does not confine itself to the Senator's letters and papers. Almost every day that Cornelius and his wife, Olive, were apart, which was a large portion of their lives, they wrote to each other. Their letters came from San Francisco and Los Angeles, from Washington, D.C. and towns in upstate New York. But Olive's letters and writings are not just the warm sentiments of a devoted wife and mother. They tell of California politics, of ambitions in the Grant Cabinet, of visits to the Centennial Exhibition in Philadelphia in 1876 and the Yosemite Valley. She served on the state committee representing California at the World Columbian Exposition in Chicago in 1893, and was the delegate-at-large from the state at the Republican National Convention of 1916. Moreover, the writing habit of Cornelius and his wife is reflected in the extensive correspondence of their eight children and dozens of relatives, even to the third and fourth generation. Cole's brother, George, writes from the battle front during the campaigns in Virginia in the Civil War. Cole's son, Willoughby, tells of life at Cornell University in the 1870s and of his long friendship with Grant's son, Jesse. Another son, George R., writes from Vienna during the 1890s. Several members of the family describe life in the territories of the Southwest when that region was still a frontier. Together, the family papers constitute a partial pattern of American life.
The general sense of the significance of these papers secured their physical preservation, even when the writer cautioned: destroy this. They were brought out of the packing trunks years later, most of them still resealed in their original envelopes. Some of them were used by Catherine C. Phillips for a biography of Cole, privately printed in 1929. But numerous volumes of history and biography remain to be written with reference to them. Through the perceptive efforts of Lindley Bynum, the papers were given to the Library of the University of California, Los Angeles, by Cole's daughter, Lucretia Waring, in 1952. Now the grand pageant of a century is opened for the appreciation and use of students of California and American history...the history which Cornelius Cole and his family lived.
E.R.R.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of material concerning the public and private career of California Senator Cornelius Cole and his family. Includes correspondence, business papers, clippings, photographs, scrap books, diaries, various writings by Cornelius and Olive Cole, and family memorabilia. The papers cover more than a century of American history including California politics, government and history, life in the Southwest, Civil War campaigns, railroads, and the crystallization of the new Republican party in Northern California.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Correspondence of Cornelius Cole (1851-1924).
Correspondence of the Cole family (1846-1940).
Business papers of Cornelius Cole and the Cole family (1850-1926).
The writings of Cornelius and Olive Cole and the Cole family (1850-1924).
Miscellaneous papers and objects (1833-1943).
Correspondence and papers of Olive Howard Waring (1898-1941).
Papers of Cole family law partnership (1886-1916).
Physical Arrangement
Correspondence of Cornelius Cole
Cole to various persons
Various persons to Cole
Cole to Olive Cole
Olive Cole to Cole
Cole to members of the Cole family
Members of the Cole family to Cole
Correspondence of the Cole Family
Olive Cole to various persons
Various persons to Olive Cole
Olive Cole to members of the Cole family
Members of the Cole family to Olive Cole
Members of the Cole family to various persons
Various persons to members of the Cole family
Business Papers of Cornelius Cole and the Cole Family
The Writings of Cornelius and Olive Cole and the Cole Family
The writings of Cornelius Cole
The writings of Olive Cole
The writings of members of the Cole family
Miscellaneous Papers and Objects
Newspaper clippings concerning Cornelius and Olive Cole and the Cole family
Newspapers and newspaper clippings concerning political subjects
Miscellaneous documents and papers
Scrapbooks concerning family and political subjects
Invitations and calling cards
Memorabilia
Photographs of members of the Cole family and of various persons
Correspondence and Papers of Olive Howard Waring
Olive Waring to various persons
Various persons to Olive Waring
Writings of Olive Waring
Miscellaneous documents and papers
Objects and memorabilia
Papers of Cole Family Law Partnerships
Within each document box, the materials are contained in folders, labeled by subject and chronological span, and arranged in a general chronological order. The user should note that some pieces may be out of this general order because of erroneous or unknown dating, or because of enclosure in or relation to another piece. In the cases of diaries and other bound volumes, each piece bears a label with the date of the contents. In the cases of such miscellaneous materials as the invitations and calling cards and the memorabilia, no chronological order is used. The photographs are arranged alphabetically by subject and surname.
Related Material
William S. Rosecrans Papers (Collection 663). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Letters to and from Cornelius Cole located at the Huntington Library, San Marino, California.
Subject Index
A list of selected letters and subjects to be used as a guide to references in the Cole papers.
Agassiz, Louis J. Box 7/folder 1868.
Akerman, Amos T.
Alabama Claims.
Alaska Purchase, 1867.
Alger, Russell A.
Allison, William B. Letter: Box 4/folder 1880-1898.
Amnesty Bill. Box 8/folder 1876.
Anarchists, Chicago. Box 11/folder 1887.
ARTHUR, CHESTER A.
Arizona.
Asiatic Commercial Company. Box 8/folder 1873.
Atchison, Topeka Railroad. Box 15/folder 3.
Australian Mail Line. Box 38/scrapbook 4.
Babcock, Orville E.
Baja California. Box 3/folder 1871.
Baker, Edward D. Box 3/folder 1871.
Baltimore, Maryland. Box 6/folder 1866.
Bancroft, George. Letter: Box 2/folder 1866-1870.
Bancroft, Hubert H.
Banks, Nathaniel.
Banning, Phineas. 3 letters: Box 3/folder 1871.
Barlow, Charles A. 2 letters: Box 4/folder 1880-1898.
Bayard, Thomas F.
Belknap, William W.
Bidwell, John.
Bidwell, Anna K. (Mrs.). Letter: Box 4/folder 1901-1909.
Biggs, Asa. 5 letters: Box 2/folder 1863-1865.
Billings, Frederick. 2 letters: Box 2/folder 1863-1865.
Bingham, John A. 5 letters: Box 3/folder 1873-1875.
Blaine, James G.
Blair, Francis P. Box 41/folder 3.
Blair, Francis P. Jr.
Blair, Montgomery.
Bond, Carrie Jacobs. 2 Letters: Box 17/folder 1892-1893.
Booth, Newton.
Boston, Massachusetts. Box 10/folder 1885.
Boutwell, George S.
Bradbury, George. 3 letters: Box 2/folder 1863-1865.
Brady, Mathew B. Box 7/folder 1872.
Brandegee, Frank B. Letter: Box 4/folder 1919-1921.
Bristow, Benjamin H.
Broderick, David C.
Brownlow, William Parson. Box 41/folder 3.
Browning, Orville H. Box 2/folder 1866-1870.
Bryan, William J. Box 4/folder 1880-1898.
Buchanan, James.
Burlingame, Anson. Box 7/folder 1868.
Burnett, Peter H.
Burnside, Ambrose.
Butler, Benjamin F.
Butler, Nicholas M. Letter: Box 18/folder 1917-1922.
Cabinets, References to Various Presidents'.
California.
California Citrus Industry.
California Emigration.
California Gold Rush, 1849.
California Indians. Box 60/folder 3.
California Journalists.
California Lands and Real Property.
California Mines and Mining.
California Politics and Government.
California Reclamation of Land.
California Wine and Wine Making Industry.
California and Texas Railroad.
California, University of.
Campbell, Thompson. 9 letters: Box 2/folder 1866-1870.
Cannon, Marion. Letter: Box 4/folder 1880-1898.
Carleton, James.
Carleton, S. (Mrs.). Letter: Box 3/folder 1871.
Caribbean Sea.
Casserly, Eugene.
Centennial Exhibition [See: Philadelphia, Centennial Exhibition, 1876].
Central Pacific Railroad.
Central Polynesian Land and Commercial Company. [See: Samoan Islands Project].
Chaffee, Adna. Letter: Box 4/folder 1901-1909.
Chandler, Zachariah.
Chase, Salmon P.
Chicago, Illinois.
Chicago, World's Columbian Exposition, 1893.
China and the Chinese Question.
Civil Rights Bill. Box 2/folder 1866-1870.
Civil War-Campaigns and Battles.
Finance. Box 3/folder 1871.
Clay, Cassius M.
Clemens, Samuel L. and Clemens, Olivia.
Cleveland, S. Grover.
Cole and Cole (Attorneys at Law, Los Angeles). Papers and documents: Boxes 44-48.
Cole, Cornelia (daughter of Cornelius Cole).
Cole, Cornelius.
Cole, David (father of Cornelius Cole).
Cole, David (brother of Cornelius Cole). Letters from: Box 15/folder 4.
Cole, Elijah (brother of Cornelius Cole). Letters from: Box 15/folder 4.
Cole, Emma (daughter of Cornelius Cole).
Cole Family and Relatives.
Cole, George R. (son of Cornelius Cole).
Cole, George T. (son of Cornelius Cole).
Cole, George W. (brother of Cornelius Cole).
Cole, Gilbert (brother of Cornelius Cole).
Cole, Grace (daughter of Cornelius Cole). Letters to: Box 15/folder 1.
Cole, Lourina (sister of Cornelius Cole).
Cole, Lucretia (daughter of Cornelius Cole).
Cole, Martha (sister of Cornelius Cole).
Cole, Olive (neé Olive Colegrove-wife of Cornelius Cole).
Cole, Rachel (mother of Cornelius Cole).
Cole, Schuyler (son of Cornelius Cole).
Cole, Seward (son of Cornelius Cole).
Cole, Willoughby (son of Cornelius Cole).
Colegrove, A.C. (father of Olive Cole). Letters from: Box 21/folder 1.
Colegrove, Brad T. (brother of Olive Cole). Letters from: Box 21/folder 2.
Colegrove Family and Relatives. Correspondence: Boxes 21 and 22.
Colegrove, Silas C. (brother of Olive Cole).
Colegrove, Susan (sister of Olive Cole).
Colfax, Schuyler.
Columbian Exposition. [See: Chicago, World's Columbian Exposition, 1893].
Commercial Companies. [See: Asiatic Commercial Company, Australian Mail Line, Mexican Steamship Company, Overland Mail Company, Pacific Mail Steamship Company, Samoan Islands Project, Wells, Fargo Company].
Congress.
Conkling, Roscoe.
Conness, John.
Constitution. [See: United States Constitution-Thirteenth Amendment].
Coolidge, Calvin.
Cornell University.
Cox, Jacob D. Box 32/folder 1.
Cox, Samuel S.
Croker, Edwin B.
Cuba.
Currency Question.
Delano, Columbus.
Democratic Party.
Dent, Frederick T.
Dodge, Grenville M. Box 3/folder 1871.
Douglas, Stephen A.
Drum, Richard C. Letter: Box 2/folder 1863-1865.
Early, Jubal A. Box 6/folder 1864.
East St. Louis, Illinois. Box 11/folder 1895-1896.
Edmunds, George F.
Edmunds, Mrs. G.F. 2 letters: Box 4/folder 1919-1921.
England. [See: Great Britain].
Evarts, William M.
Fessenden, William P.
Field, Stephen J.
Fish, Hamilton.
Fiske, John. Box 10/folder 1885.
Flint, Frank P.
Foote, Henry S. Box 4/folder 3.
Franco-German War, 1870-1871.
Fremont, John C.
Fremont, Jessie Benton (Mrs.). Letter: Box 18/folder, n.d.
French Spoliation Claims. Box 10/folder 1885.
Gardner, Alexander.
Garfield, James A.
Georgetown University. Box 8/folder 1875.
Germany.
Gilman, Daniel C. 3 letters: Box 3/folder 1873-1875.
Goat Island, San Francisco, Project.
Goldstone, Louis Memorial & Obituary Box 5/folder 1922.
Grace, William R. 3 letters: Box 3/folder 1873-1875.
Grand Army of the Republic. Box 10/folder 1886.
Grant, Ulysses S. Telegram: Box 16/folder 1870-1880.
Grant, U.S., and the Grant Family.
Grant, Julia Dent (Mrs.). Letter: Box 16/folder 1870-1880.
Grant, Jesse.
Grant, U.S. Jr.
Great Britain.
Haight, Henry H.
Hamlin, Hannibal.
Hammond, John H. 2 letters and a telegram: Box 5/folder 1922.
Harding, Warren G.
Harlan, James. Box 14/folder 1884.
Hay-Pauncefote Treaty, 1901. Box 28/folder 3.
Hayes, Rutherford B.
Hays, Will H.
Herrick, Myron B. Box 52/folder 2.
Historical Society of Southern California.
Hittell, [John?]. Box 11/folder 1887.
Holladay, Ben. Box 2/folder 1863-1865.
Hollywood High School, Los Angeles.
Hopkins, Mark.
Howe, Timothy O. 2 letters: Box 3/folder 1871.
Hughes, Charles E.
Hunt, Rockwell D.
Huntington, Collis P.
Huntington, Henry E.
Idaho. Box 2/folder 1863-1865.
Illinois.
Independent Party of California. Box 16/folder 1870-1880.
Indian Affairs, Bureau of.
Ingersoll, Ebon C. Letter: Box 3/folder 1871.
Ingersoll, Robert G.
Johnson, Andrew.
Johnson, Hiram.
Johnson, Reverdy.
Jones, John P.
Kansas.
Kearny, Dennis. Box 3/folder 1876-1879.
Kleinsmid, Rufus B. von.
Ku Klux Klan Bill.
Lake Tahoe, California.
Lane, Allan M. 8 letters: Box 2/folder 1863-1865.
Lansing, Robert. Letter: Box 4/folder 1915-1918.
Latham, Milton S. Letter: Box 2/Folder 1866-70.
League of Nations.
Le Conte, Joseph. Box 10/folder 1885.
Lee, Robert E. Box 28/folder 4.
Lincoln, Abraham.
Lincoln, Robert T. Box 12/folder 1868.
Logan, John A.
Logan, Mrs. John A.
London. Box 3/folder 1871.
Los Angeles.
Los Angeles Harbor Controversy.
Low, Frederick F.
Lowden, Frank O. Telegram: Box 5/folder 1924.
Lummis, Charles F.
McAdoo, William G.
McClatchy, James.
McClellan, George B.
McCulloch, Hugh. Box 2/folder 1866-1870.
McDowell, Irvin. Box 52/folder 3.
McKinley, William.
Maltby, Charles.
Mexican Steamship Company. Box 3/folder 1871.
Mexico.
Mitchell, John H. Letter: Box 4/folder 1880-1898.
Modoc Indians.
Morgan, Edwin D.
Motley, John L.
Morton, Oliver P.
Mt. Vernon, Virginia.
Needham, James C. Letter: Box 49/folder 3.
Negroes: Slaves and Freedmen.
Negro Extradition Case, Sacramento, California, 1852.
Nevada. Box 8/folder 1875.
New Constitutional Party, California. Box 3/folder 1876-1879.
New Mexico.
New York State.
Northern Railroad. Box 8/folder 1873.
Ogden, Utah. Box 7/folder 1871.
Olney, Richard. Box 4/folder 1880-1898.
Omaha, Nebraska.
Ord, Edward. Letter: Box 2/folder 1866-1870.
Oregon Canyon, California.
Osborne, Henry Z. Letter: Box 4/folder 1919-1921.
Overland Mail Company. Box 2/folder 1863-1865.
Pacific Islands. [See: Samoan Islands Project].
Pacific Mail Steamship Company.
Pacific Railroad.
Panama.
Parrott, Enoch G.
Patti, Adelina.
Penrose, Boies. Letter: Box 4/folder 1919-1921.
Perkins, George C.
Peru. Box 3/folder 1873-1875.
Philadelphia, Centennial Exhibition, 1876.
Phillips, Catherine C.
Photographs-Wrapped Separately
Pony Express, California. Box 29/folder 1.
Populist Party. Box 36/envelope 5.
Pratt, James.
Pratt, Orson. Box 7/folder 1872.
Progressive Party.
Public Lands, Office of.
Ralston, William C.
Railroads.
Ranchos Témescal and Sobrante, California. Box 2/folder 1866-1870.
Randall, Charles H. Letter: Box 4/folder 1919-1921.
Reconstruction Policy, 1866-1876.
Republican League of California. Box 4/folder 1880-1898.
Republican Party.
Richardson, Albert D. Box 7/folder 1869.
Riddick, Carl W. Letter: Box 5/folder 1923.
Robeson, George. Letter: Box 3/folder 1871.
Roosevelt, Theodore.
Root, Elihu. Box 1/folder 1913-1919.
Rosecrans, Carl F. Letter: Box 5/folder 1922.
Russian-American Fur Company.
Salt Lake City, Utah. Box 7/folder 1868.
St. Louis, Missouri. Box 11/folder 1895-1896.
Samoan Islands Project.
San Diego, California.
San Francisco.
Santa Fe, New Mexico. Box 15/folder 3.
Santo Domingo.
Sargent, Aaron A.
Schurz, Carl.
Senate of the United States.
Severance, Caroline S.M. Box 18/folder 1894-1913.
Seward, Clarence A. Letter: Box 2/folder 1866-1870.
Seward, Frederick W.
Seward, William H.
Sherman, John.
Sherman, William T.
Sherman, Ellen E. (Mrs.). 3 letters: Box 16/folder 1870-1880.
Shortridge, Samuel M. Letter: Box 4/folder 1919-1921.
Simonton, James W.
Siringo Charles A: 9 letters: Box 50/folder 2.
Smithsonian Institution. Box 6/folder 1865.
Society of California Pioneers.
Southern Pacific Railroad.
Spain, War With, 1898.
Spalding, A.G.
Sprague, William. Letter: Box 3/folder 1872.
Spreckels, Adolph. Box 1/folder 1880-1912.
Squire, Watson C. Letter: Box 18/folder 1917-1922.
Stanford, Leland.
Stanley, Edward.
Stanton, Edwin M.
Stearns, Abel. 4 letters: Box 2/folder 1866-1870.
Stephens, William D.
Stevens, Robert J. 4 letters: Box 3/folder 1871.
Stewart, J.M.B.
Stewart, William M.
Stevenot, Gabriel K. 5 letters: Box 3/folder 1873-1875.
Stevens, Thaddeus.
Stoeckl, Edouard, Baron de.
Sumner, Charles.
Sutter, John A.
Sutter's Fort. Box 5/folder 1923.
Taft, William H.
Tariffs: U.S.
Telegraph Line Construction Projects, California.
Texas-Pacific Railroad.
Tracy, F.P.
Truman, Benjaminc. Letter: Box 18/folder 1894-1913.
Trumbull, Lyman.
United Republicans of Southern California. Box 4/folder 1915-1918.
United States Constitution-Thirteenth Amendment. Box 6/folder 1865.
University of Southern California, Los Angeles.
Utah.
Virginia.
Wade, Benjamin F.
War Premiums Bill. Box 8/folder 1876.
Waring, Howards. Box 43A.
Waring, Olive Howard (granddaughter of Cornelius Cole).
Washburne, Elihu B.
Washington, D.C.
Washington, Treaty of, 1871.
Watson, James E.
Welles, Gideon.
Wells, Fargo Company. Box 2/folder 1863-1865.
Wesleyan University, Connecticut.